Register of the Tom Killion papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Subject File, 1868-1997 (Boxes 6-20)
  - Horn of Africa, 1868-1997
    - Politics, Ethiopia
      - Orality, State Literacy, and Political Culture in Ethiopia: Translating the Ras Kassa Registers [McCann, James C.], 1991 (Box-folder 17: 7)
      - "Policy Declaration of the Provisional Military Government to Solve the Problem in the Administrative Region of Eritrea in a Peaceful Way,", 1976 (Box-folder 17: 8)
      - "The Legacy of Eritrea’s National Question" [Pateman, Roy, Society], 1996 (Box-folder 17: 9)
      - "The Spread of Marxism-Leninism in Ethiopia" [Sherr, E.], 1980s (Box-folder 17: 10)
    - Politics, Horn of Africa
      - Africa Confidential, article clippings, 1981-1992 (Box-folder 17: 11)
      - "Anti-Colonialism and Class Formation: The Eastern Horn of Africa before 1950" [Geshekter, Charles L., The International Journal of African Historical Studies], 1985 (Box-folder 17: 12)
      - Eritrea and Tigray, 5th edition, 1983 (Box-folder 17: 13)
      - From Conflict to Concord: Regional Cooperation in the Horn of Africa [United States Economic Commission for Africa], 1993 (Box-folder 17: 14)
      - Italian Africa, "A un anno dal manifesto razzista,", 1939 (Box-folder 17: 15)
      - Italian Africa, "Manodopera indigena nell’ A.O.I.,", 1939 (Box-folder 18: 1)
      - Italian Africa, "Razza nazionlità ittadinanza,", 1938 (Box-folder 18: 2)
      - "Questione agraria e questione nazionale in Eritrea in Ethiopia e in Somalia,", 1977 (Box-folder 18: 3)
      - The Carter Center ["Carter Convenes Historic Ethiopian/Eritrean Peace Talks"], 1989 (Box-folder 18: 4)
    - Politics, Somalia
      - "Entrepreneurs, Livestock, and Politics: British Somaliland, 1920-1950" [Geshekter, Charles L.], 1982 (Box-folder 18: 5)
      - "Transfrontier Society: Somali Responses to the Imposition of British, Italian and Ethiopian Rule, 1900-1920," [Samatar, Said S.], undated (Box-folder 18: 6)
    - Politics, Sudan
      - "British Policy in Southern Sudan and the Problem of National Integration, 1898-1956,", 1989 (Box-folder 18: 7)
      - "Ethnicity and Politics in the Red Sea Province, Sudan" [Morton, John, African Affairs], 1989 (Box-folder 18: 8)
      - "Food, Wages, and Profits: Mechanized Schemes and the Sudanese State," [Bascom, Johnathan B., Economic Geography], 1990 (Box-folder 18: 9)
    - Population - Eritrea, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 18: 10)
    - Proclamations, Ethiopia
      - "An Order to Provide for the Establishment of a Public Employment Administration" [ Negarit Gazeta], 1962 (Box-folder 18: 11)
      - "Labor Proclamation," Transitional Government of Ethiopia [ Negarit Gazeta], 1993 (Box-folder 18: 12)
      - "Trade Unions Organization Proclamation" [ Negarit Gazeta], 1982 (Box-folder 18: 13)
    - Referendum, Eritrea
      - "Camel-Dance and Balloting: The Afar Factor in the Referendum on Independence for Eritrea" [Tronvoll, Kjetil, The Horn of Africa Review], 1994 (Box-folder 18: 14)
      - "Trip Report on African-American Institute Mission to Observe the Eritrean Referendum,", 1993 (Box-folder 18: 15)
    - Refugees, Horn of Africa - Ethiopia/Somalia, 1991 (Box-folder 18: 16)
    - Refugees, Sudan
      - "Border Pastoralism in Eastern Sudan" [Bascom, Johnathan B., Geographical Review], 1990 (Box-folder 18: 17)
      - Briefing note on refugees in Sudan, 1987 (Box-folder 18: 18)
      - "Constraints on Assistance to Refugees: Some Observations from the Sudan" [Karadawi, Ahmed, World Development], 1983 (Box-folder 18: 19)
      - "Epidemiological Assessment of the Health and Nutrition of Ethiopian Refugees in Emergency Camps in Sudan, 1985" [Shears, Paul, et al., British Medical Journal], 1987 (Box-folder 18: 20)
      - "Eritrea Refugees in Sudan" [Johnson, Trish, Disasters], 1979 (Box-folder 18: 21)
      - "Eritreans in Kassala," research project from University of Khartoum, 1987 (Box-folder 18: 22)
      - "Refugees and Development: Dissonance in Sudan" Kilgour, Mary C., Middle East Journal], 1990 (Box-folder 18: 23)
      - "Repatriation Prospects for Unassisted Eritreans in Eastern Sudan,", 1993 (Box-folder 18: 24)
      - Safawa, Sudan, typed essay, 1987 (Box-folder 18: 25)
      - "Sudan Journal" [Costello Daly, Celine], 1993 (Box-folder 18: 26)
      - Wad Kowli Refugee Camp, 1986 (Box-folder 18: 27)
      - "The Refugee Problem" [Berhane, W., Sudanow], 1977 (Box-folder 18: 28)
    - Refugees, world - "Mortality Trends in Refugee Emergencies: An Analysis of Refugee Populations in Thailand, Somalia, and Sudan" [Toole, Michael J., and Waldman, Ronald J.], 1988 (Box-folder 18: 29)
    - Rehabilitation, Eritrea
      - Efforts at social rehabilitation, 1993 (Box-folder 18: 30)
      - The recovery and rehabilitation programme for Eritrea, 1993 (Box-folder 18: 31)
    - Relief, Eritrea
      - Eritrean Relief Association (ERA), 1986-1987 (Box-folder 18: 32)
      - Eritrean Relief Association ["ERA Alerts on a Severe Food Crisis Overchanging Eritrea"], 1987-1988 (Box-folder 19: 1)
      - Eritrean Relief Committee (ERC), 1988 statistics (Box-folder 19: 2)
      - Eritrean Relief Committee Newsletter, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 19: 3)
    - Relief, Ethiopia - Relief Society of Tigray (RST) ["Tigray Revisited by Famine," Relief Society of Tigray Bulletin], 1987 (Box-folder 19: 4)
    - Religion - L’evangelo d’oro di Dabra Libanos, 1901 (Box-folder 19: 5)
    - Reports
      - Referendum Eritrea: The African American Institute (AAI) International Delegation Observer, 1993 April 23-25 (Box-folder 19: 6)
      - Ethiopia: ACR, 1971-1988 (Box-folder 19: 7)
    - Research - 11th International Conference on Ethiopian Studies, 1991 (Box-folder 19: 8)
      Includes brochures, flyers, pamphlet, programs, and abstracts.
    - Revolution
      - "Popular Participation in the Ethiopian Revolution,", undated (Box-folder 19: 9)
      - "The Ethiopian Revolution: Mythology and History" [Henze, Paul B., Northeast African Studies], 1989 (Box-folder 19: 10)
    - Rules, Ethiopia - "Rules and Regulations," Wonji Club, 1969 (Box-folder 19: 11)
    - Thesis - NEGASSA, Emmanuel’s thesis dedicated to the Ethiopian worker, circa 1976 (Box-folder 19: 12)
    - Tradition, Eritrea - Publication of the Princeton Expedition to Abyssinia, Vol. II, Tigre tribes, 1910 (Box-folder 19: 13)
    - Travel, Ethiopia - 27 November to 6 December, 1966 (Box-folder 19: 14)
    - Women, Eritrea
      - "Eritrea’s Unfinished Revolution: From Women’s Nationalist Mobilization to Post-War Gender Politics, 1970-1996," (Box-folder 19: 15)
      - "My Name Is Woman" [Sister Dolores Smith], undated (Box-folder 20: 1)
      - "Women and Liberation Movements: The Case of Eritrea" [Hale, Sondra, African Studies Center Newsletter], 1994 (Box-folder 20: 2)
    - Women, Sudan - "Rotating and Escalating Credit in the Female Domain: The Sandug of Central Sudan" [Kenyon, Susan M.], 1997 (Box-folder 20: 3)
    - Youth - Eritrean Youth Newsletter, 1997 (Box-folder 20: 4)
      Includes an article clipping from the San Francisco Chronicle and a quarterly newsletter from the African Studies Association.
  - World, 1967-1990, undated
    - Article - "What Makes Peasants Revolutionary?" [Skocpol, Theda, Comparative Politics], 1982 (Box-folder 20: 5)
    - Book review - "Antonin Besse of Aden: The Founder of St. Antony’s College, Oxford" [Schaefer, Charles], 1986 (Box-folder 20: 6)
    - Demobilization - "Désarmement et déflation au sortir des conflits: enjeux et procédures" [Marchal, Roland], circa 1990 (Box-folder 20: 7)
    - Economics - "The Stages of the Evolution of Capitalism into Imperialism," handwritten essay by unknown author, undated (Box-folder 20: 8)
    - Union leaders - "How the CIA Makes Liars out of Union Leaders" [Jacobs, Paul], 1967 (Box-folder 20: 9)
- Printed Matter, 1961-1996 (Boxes 20-25)
  Includes magazines produced by the Eritrean People’s Liberation Front (EPLF), Confederation of Ethiopian Labor Union (CELU), and other organizations, as well as journal articles. For newspapers and newspaper clippings, see Oversize Materials.
  - Adulis [Central Bureau of Foreign Relations of the Eritrean People's Liberation Front], 1984-1991 (Box-folder 20: 10-15)
  - Africa News, 1980 (Box-folder 20: 16)
  - Africa Watch [Committee of Human Rights Watch], 1990 (Box-folder 20: 17)
  - African Studies Association (ASA), Manual of Policies and Procedures, 1995 (Box-folder 20: 18)
  - Awet Ne Hafash, newsletter of Democratic Eritreans in North America, 1979 (Box-folder 20: 19)
  - Brochure, Your Guide to Ethiopia, the Land of the Queen of Sheba, undated (Box-folder 20: 20)
  - Brochures, 1990 (Box-folder 20: 21)
    Brochures from Addis Ababa University include the Society of Friends from the Institute of Ethiopian Studies and The Book Centre.
  - Chibaro: African Mine Labour in Southern Rhodesia, 1900-1933 [van Onselen, Charles], preface, 1976 (Box-folder 20: 22)
  - "Cultural Aspects of the Industrial Revolution: Lynn, Massachusetts, Shoemakers and Industrial Morality, 1826-1860" [Faler, Paul, Labor History], 1974 (Box-folder 20: 23)
  - Dimtsi Hafash
    - Vol. 1, No. 2, 1979 (Box-folder 20: 24)
    - Vol. 1, No. 15; Vol. 2, Nos. 3, 6, 13/14, 1980 (Box-folder 20: 25)
    - Vol. 2, Nos. 20-22, undated (Box-folder 20: 26)
  - Eritrea, articles, 1979-1995 (Box-folder 21: 1)
    Includes articles from The Guardian, Current History, Time, Africa Research Bulletin, and The Atlantic.
  - Eritrea Bulletin, 1983-1984, 1992 (Box-folder 21: 2)
  - Eritrea Information
    - 1980-1986 (Box-folder 21: 3-9)
    - Index (1979-1982) (Box-folder 21: 10)
  - Eritrea in Relief [Eritrean Relief Association], 1986 (Box-folder 21: 11)
  - Eritrea in the Western Media [Concerned Americans and Eritreans of the San Francisco Bay Area], 1988 (Box-folder 21: 12)
  - Eritrea Now [Eritrean People's Liberation Front], Vol. 1, No. 5, 1979 (Box-folder 21: 13)
  - Eri-TV, A Tool for Education and Social Change, pamphlet, 1991 (Box-folder 21: 14)
  - Eritrea Update
    - 1992-1994 cumulative subject index (Box-folder 21: 15)
    - 1992-1994 (Box-folder 21: 16-18)
  - "Eritrea Wins the Peace" [Cobb, Charles E., Jr., National Geographic], 1996 (Box-folder 22: 1)
  - Eritrean People's Liberation Front, declaration ["Statement Concerning the New Declaration of the Dergue"], 1989 (Box-folder 22: 2)
  - Eritrean People’s Liberation Front, press release ["An Important Declaration"], 1980-1982 (Box-folder 22: 3)
  - Eritrean Relief Committee, ERC Newsletter, 1983-1986, 1991 (Box-folder 22: 4)
  - Eritrean Relief Committe, USA Annual Report, 1985 (Box-folder 22: 5)
  - Eritrean Studies Association (ESA) Newsletter [Connell, Dan, "Eritrea: Starting from Scratch," Review of African Political Economy], 1995 (Box-folder 22: 6)
  - The Eritrean, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 22: 7-8)
  - The Eritrean Newsletter, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 22: 9)
  - "The Eritrean Struggle" [Eritrean People's Liberation Front], 1991 (Box-folder 22: 10)
  - United States Committee for a Free Eritrea (FREE) [ Eritrea Free], 1990-1991 (Box-folder 22: 11)
  - Ethiopia, articles, 1980-1992 (Box-folder 22: 12)
    Includes articles published by Africa Confidential, The Ethiopian Observer, The Ethiopian, Los Angeles Times, New York Times and the Africa Report.
  - "Ethiopia in Turmoil" [ New African], 1989 (Box-folder 22: 13)
  - Ethiopian Herald ["Woman Victim Tells Her Story"], 1974 (Box-folder 22: 14)
  - Friends of Ethiopia Newsletter, Vol 1., Nos. 1-2, 1991 (Box-folder 22: 15)
  - Foreign Broadcast Information Service (FBIS), Horn of Africa, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 22: 16)
    Includes small articles from unknown publishers about East Africa.
  - "From Peasants to Workers in Africa" [Cohen, Robin, in The Political Economy of Contemporary Africa], 1976 (Box-folder 22: 17)
  - Horn of Africa Bulletin, 1996 (Box-folder 22: 18)
  - Hugh’s News [Lalmba Association], Vol. 27, No. 3, circa 1990 (Box-folder 22: 19)
  - Liberation, 1976-1977, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 22: 20)
  - Middle East Research and Information Project (MERIP), 1979-1985 (Box-folder 23: 1-6)
  - MERIP Middle East Report
    - 1986 (Box-folder 23: 7)
    - 1988-1993 (Box-folder 24: 1-6)
  - Newspaper, The Ethiopian Herald, 1961 (Box-folder 24: 7)
  - People’s Voice, Foreign Relations Bureau, Tigray People's Liberation Front, Vol. 1, No. 1, 1985 (Box-folder 24: 8)
  - Press clippings, 1993 (Box-folder 24: 9)
    Related to Eritrean independence.
  - Press release from the Democratic Eritreans in North America (DENA), 1979 (Box-folder 24: 10)
  - Resistance, newsletter of National Union of Eritrean Students (NUES), Vol. 2, Nos. 2-3, 1980 (Box-folder 24: 11)
  - Revolution, monthly publication of ELF-PLF, 12th year, No. 8, 1973 (Box-folder 24: 12)
  - Sagem, No. 11, special edition, 1988 (Box-folder 24: 13)
  - Tatek, magazine of Revolutionary Ethiopia’s Armed Forces, 1986 (Box-folder 24: 14)
    1978 Coptic or Ethiopian Calendar / 1986 Gregorian calendar.
  - "The Creation of Group Consciousness Among the Dockworkers of Dar es Salaam, 1929-1950" [Iliffe, John, in The Development of an African Working Class: Studies in Class Formation and Action], 1975 (Box-folder 25: 1)
  - The Development of an African Working Class: Studies in Class Formation and Action, introduction, 1976 (Box-folder 25: 2)
  - "The Formation of a Working Class in Kenya" [Stichter, Sharon, in The Development of an African Working Class: Studies in Class Formation and Action], 1976 (Box-folder 25: 3)
  - "The 'Labor Aristocracy' in Africa: Introduction to a Debate" [Waterman, Peter, Development and Change], 1975 (Box-folder 25: 4)
  - "'The Regiment of the Hills': South Africa’s Lumpenproletarian Army, 1890-1920" [van Onselen, Charles, Past & Present], 1978 (Box-folder 25: 5)
  - "Third World Strikes: An Invitation to Discussion" [Waterman, Peter, Development and Change], 1976 (Box-folder 25: 6)
  - "Third World Strikes in International Perspective" [Hyman, Richard, Development and Change], 1979 (Box-folder 25: 7)
  - "Time, Work-Discipline, and Industrial Capitalism" [Thompson, E. P., Past & Present], 1967 (Box-folder 25: 8)
  - "Transport Workers, Strikes and the 'Imperial Response': Africa and the Post World War II Conjuncture" [Oberst, Timothy, African Studies Review], 1988 (Box-folder 25: 9)
  - "Union Leaders, Worker Organization and Strikes: Karachi, 1969-1972" [Shaheed, Zafar, Development and Change], 1979 (Box-folder 25: 10)
  - Vanguard, Eritrean People's Liberation Front, Vol. 2, No. 5, 1977 (Box-folder 25: 11)
  - Vietnam: A Thousand Years of Struggle, 1969 (Box-folder 25: 12)
  - "Worker Consciousness in Black Miners: Southern Rhodesia, 1900-1920" [van Onselen, Charles, The Journal of African History], 1973 (Box-folder 25: 13)
  - "Workers: From Labor Migration to Proletarianization" [Coquery-Vidrovitch, Catherine, chapter in Africa: Endurance and Change South of the Sahara], 1988 (Box-folder 25: 14)
- Photographs, 1960s (Box-folder 25: 15)
  One large photograph of Arnold Zack, Beyene Solomon, and Seyoum.
- Miscellaneous, 1947-1990 (Box 25)
  - Chemin de Fer Djibouti-Éthiopie (CFE), 1947-1969, and other items (Box-folder 25: 16)
  - Eritrea: Against All Odds, book cover, 1990 (Box-folder 25: 17)
- Oversize Materials, 1944, 1991-1997 (Boxes 26-29)
  Newspapers and newspaper clippings.
  - Semunawi Gazetta/ The Eritrean Weekly News, 100th issue, 1944 (Box 26)
  - Haddas Eritrea/ New Eritrea
    - Vol. 1, Nos. 2–6, 8, 9, 13, 14, 17, 19, 21-26, 27-35, 1991 September-December (Box 26)
    - Vol. 1, Nos. 37, 39-45, 47-50, 52-73, 80-86, 1992 January-June (Box 26)
  - Eritrea Profile
    - Vol. 1, Nos. 3, 6-8, 10-11, 16-17, 23-25, 27, 37-42, 1994 April-December (Box 27)
    - Vol. 1, Nos. 43-52, Vol. 2, Nos. 1-14, 1995 January-June (Box 27)
    - Vol. 2, Nos. 16-21, 23-42, 1995 July-December (Box 27)
    - Vol. 2, Nos. 43-51; Vol. 3, Nos. 20-30, 32-42, 1996 January-December (Box 27)
    - Vol. 3, Nos. 43-52; Vol. 4, Nos. 1-16, 1997 January-June (Box 28)
    - Vol. 4, Nos. 17-20, 22-39, 41-42, 1997 July-December
  - Horn of Africa newspaper clippings, undated (Box 29)
- Index Cards, 1980s-1990s (Box 30)
  Includes notes on different industries, labor unions, and manufacturing of Ethiopia, as well as one microfilm reel copy of a Syracuse University dissertation (awarded in 1975) entitled, "The Greeks in Ethiopia, Economic, Political and Social Life, c. 1740-1936."
  - A. Besse and Co.
  - Background, African labor history
  - Background, Italian colonial
  - CELU
  - CFFE (RR)
  - Cloth and textile industry
  - Coffee
  - Dire Dawa
  - Djibouti
  - Ethiopia, background (political history)
  - Ethiopia, economic (general)
  - Ethiopia, legal, law, and unions
  - Ethiopian revolution
  - Ethiopian Airlines (EAL)
  - HVA and sugar in general
  - Ideology of labor unions
  - Idir, Equib, and co-ops
  - Italian period
  - Labor (general, 1950s-1960s)
  - Mitchell Cotts and Co.
  - Plantations, CADU, etc.
  - Printing
  - Sabean utility
  - Salt/oil/Assab
  - Urban patterns
  - Wood, cement, shoes, bottle manufacturers, etc.
  - The Greeks in Ethiopia, economic, political, and social life, 1740-1936, 1975; 1.0 microfilm reel
- Sound Recordings, 1980s, 1994 (Box 31)
  Interviews with various Eritrean and Ethiopian labor leaders.
  - Cassettes, 1994
    - Azien Yassin, 2.0 sound cassettes
    - Port workers of Massawa, 1.0 sound cassette
  - Microcassettes, circa 1980s
    - Fissehatsion Tekie, 2.0 sound microcassettes
    - Emmanuel Negassa, 1.0 sound microcassette
    - Gebreselassie Gebremariam, 2.0 sound microcassettes
    - Mesfin, 1.0 sound microcassette
    - Paster Yohannes, 4.0 sound microcassettes
    - Tsegai Kahsai, 1.0 sound microcassette
    - Woldeab Woldemariam, 4.0 sound microcassettes